Guide to the Lionel W. McKenzie Papers, 1942-2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lionel W. McKenzie papers 1942-2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McKenzie, Lionel W.
22 linear feet Extent: 16,500 Items
Lionel McKenzie (1919-2010) was an economist whose main areas of research were general equilbrium theory and turnpike theory. McKenzie began his career as an assistant professor at Duke University from 1948 to 1957 before becoming chairman of the Economics Department at the University of Rochester in 1957, where he taught until his retirement in 1989. McKenzie also served on a number of prominent international economic organizations, where he helped to further the discourse in the discipline. Collection contains correspondence, writings, research notes, and other written material from throughout McKenzie's career. The papers span the years 1942-2004 and document his work as an economic theorist and educator.
RL.00877
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lionel W. McKenzie Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003.
Biographical Note
1919 Jan. 26 Born in Montezuma, Georgia
1939 Completed Bachelor of the Arts at Duke University
1939 Named Rhodes Scholar
1942 Completed Masters of the Arts at Princeton University
1948 Completed B. Litt. degree at Oxford University
1948-1957 Served as Assistant Professor in Economics, Duke University
1956 Received PhD from Princeton University
1957-1966 Professor and Chairman of the Department of Economics, University of Rochester
1959 Published "On the Existence of General Equilibrium for a Competitive Economy" in Econometrica
1967-1989 Served as Wilson Professor of Economics at University of Rochester
1973-1974 Awarded Guggenheim Fellowship
1978 Elected to the National Academy of Sciences
1986 Published "Optimal Growth, Turnpike Theorem, and Comparative Dynamics" in Handbook of Mathematical Economics
1989 Retired from University of Rochester
2002 Published Classical General Equilibrium Theory
2010 Oct. 12 Died in Rochester, N.Y.
Collection Overview
The Lionel W. McKenzie Papers span the years 1942 to 2004, with the bulk of the material dating from 1960 to 1990. Through correspondence, research notes, article drafts, teaching material, lectures, and published materials, the collection provides a broad overview of his professional career. McKenzie's greatest contribution to economics has been through his work in conjunction with Kenneth Arrow and Gerard Debreu on general equilibrium, and his writings on capital theory and turnpike theory, all of which are documented in a variety of forms throughout the collection. Significant correspondents include noted economists Paul Samuelson, Tjalling Koopmans, and Robert Solow. Other aspects of his career are documented, such as his involvement in a number of economic organizations, especially the Econometric Society and the Mathematical Social Sciences Board; his role as organizer of a number of academic conferences, such as the Value and Capital Conference of 1988; and his teaching career at Duke University from 1948 to 1957 and at the University of Rochester from 1957 to 1989. The papers are organized into the following series: Conferences; Correspondence; Course Materials; Organizations; Personal Files; and Research and Writings.
The Conferences Series includes material from conferences McKenzie attended and organized throughout his career and includes copies of programs, articles given, and other related documents. The Correspondence Series, the largest of the collection, contains largely official and routine correspondence, but also includes a sizeable number of letters on intellectual topics. The Research and Writings Series, the second largest, has various drafts and iterations of most of McKenzie's published work as well as some unpublished material. Many of the notes contain complicated mathematical notations documenting the theoretical foundations for his work. A small set of writings by others, chiefly on game theory and convex sets, conclude the series. The Course Materials Series houses syllabi and other materials from the seminars he taught, including many versions of the handwritten text for his general equilibrium seminar, documenting his teaching methods as well as the evolution in his thinking on the subject. In the Organizations Series, extensive documentation can be found of McKenzie's involvement with various economic organizations, including internal discussions on the workings of many of these groups. The smallest group of records, the Personal Files Series, contains curriculum vitae, personal correspondence, and other ephemera.
McKenzie Materials in Other Institutions
Other papers, chiefly correspondence and departmental files, are located at the University of Rochester, N.Y., and relate mainly to McKenzie's teaching career and professional activities at that institution. An inventory of those holdings is located in the Lionel W. McKenzie Papers public information file in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at Duke.
Also, the Institute of Economic Research at Kyoto University in Japan has established the McKenzie Library, which holds published works and other printed materials on economics from McKenzie's personal library. A printed catalog of these holdings can be found in the Lionel W. McKenzie Papers held in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at Duke.
Related Material
Those interested in Lionel McKenzie and his research may also wish to consult the Kenneth J. Arrow Papers and the Robert M. Solow Papers, also housed at the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Subject Headings
Arrow, Kenneth Joseph, 1921-; Debreu, Gerard; Koopmans, Tjalling Charles, 1910-; Samuelson, Paul Anthony, 1915-; Solow, Robert M.; University of Rochester. Dept. of Economics; Duke University. Dept. of Economics; Economics -- Teaching; Economists -- Correspondence; Economists -- United States; Equilibrium (Economics); Turnpike theory (Economics); Econometric Society; Mathematical Social Sciences Board; Value and Capital Conference
Contents of Collection
- Conferences Series, 1957-1992, (5 boxes)
  Chiefly programs, articles, minutes, correspondence, and other materials from academic conferences McKenzie attended or helped organize, both domestically and abroad. Includes some bound volumes, mostly from the 1960s, with every paper given at a particular conference. The largest amount of material comes from the 1988 Value and Capital Conference, which includes correspondence with various contributors as well as paper manuscripts for publication. Some folders include materials from non-conference related activies that occurred while McKenzie attended conferences, chiefly concert programs, maps, receipts, travel plans, and other materials. Folders are organized chronologically by year (and month, when possible).
  - 1957, Summer program at Stanford (Box 1)
  - 1958, Social Sciences Research Council (SSRC) (Box 1)
  - 1959, Stanford (Box 1)
  - 1963, Cambridge (Box 1)
  - 1964, SSRC, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1964, Outgoing correspondence for SSRC (Box 1)
  - 1964 July, Rochester, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1965 July, Stanford (Box 2)
  - 1966 Aug., Harvard (Box 2)
  - 1967 Nov., Chicago (Box 2)
  - 1968 June, Brown University (Box 2)
  - 1970, Novosibirsk (Box 3)
  - 1970 June, Vienna (Box 3)
  - 1972 July, Warsaw (Box 3)
  - 1974 July, Warsaw (Box 3)
  - 1975 Feb., National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER) (Box 3)
  - 1975 Apr., World food conference (Box 3)
  - 1976 Feb., General equilibrium, Berkeley (Box 3)
  - 1978, Montreal (Box 3)
  - 1979, Berkeley symposium (Box 3)
  - 1979, Atlanta (Box 3)
  - 1981 Aug., Cornell (Box 3)
  - 1982 June, Oxford (Box 3)
  - 1983, Minnesota (Box 3)
  - 1984 Apr., Minnesota, general equilibrium (Box 3)
  - 1985 May, Greece trip (Box 3)
  - 1985 June, Cowles conference, remarks on Debreu (Box 3)
  - 1985 Aug., MIT, econometric world conference (Box 3)
  - 1986, California trip (Box 3)
  - 1988, Value and Capital Conference, Bologna Subseries (Box 4)
    Folders include correspondence and paper drafts by the person named in the folder title.
    - Hicks conference (Box 4)
    - Amendola (Box 4)
    - Arrow (Box 4)
    - Atsumi (Box 4)
    - Brock (Box 4)
    - Casarosa (Box 4)
    - Cass (Box 4)
    - Duffie (Box 4)
    - Epstein (Box 4)
    - Gale (Box 4)
    - Geanakoplos (Box 4)
    - Grandmont (Box 4)
    - Hahn (Box 4)
    - Hall (Box 4)
    - Hamouda (Box 4)
    - Hicks (Box 4)
    - Hildenbrand (Box 4)
    - Hillebrandt (Box 4)
    - King (Box 4)
    - Laroque (Box 5)
    - Malinvaud (Box 5)
    - Masera (Box 5)
    - McKenzie (Box 5)
    - Mukherji (Box 5)
    - Patinkin (Box 5)
    - Persson (Box 5)
    - Povey (Box 5)
    - Punzo (Box 5)
    - Radner (Box 5)
    - Sonderman (Box 5)
    - Spaventa (Box 5)
    - Svensson (Box 5)
    - Uzawa (Box 5)
    - Yaari (Box 5)
    - Zamagni (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
  - 1989, Retirement conference (Box 5)
  - 1992, Minnesota (Box 5)
  - 1992, Japan trip, Hitobashi conference (Box 5)
- Correspondence Series, 1948-2003 and undated, (13 boxes)
  Mainly professional correspondence, including letters of recommendation, comments on manuscripts, advising exchanges, and topics in economics. Much of the correspondence is routine, dealing with article submissions, publication issues, recommendations, and activies relating to the Department of Economics at the University of Rochester; however, there are some intellectual exchanges and article revisions and commentaries in the series. Important topics in economics include optimal growth, turnpike theorem, general equilibrium, and Von Neumann models. Correspondents of note include Kenneth Arrow, Gerard Debreu, David Gale, Tjalling Koopmans, Paul Samuelson, and Robert Solow. There are smaller amounts of topic-specific correspondence in the Research and Writings, Conferences, and Organizations Series.
  The series is organized chronologically at the folder level, with original folder titles retained. Within folders, the organization varies from year to year: from 1948 to 1957, items are roughly chronological by date; from 1957 to 1981, items are separated into incoming and outgoing correspondence, organized alphabetically by sender and recipient, respectively; from 1981 to 1994, items are in reverse chronological order by date within folders; from 1994 to 2002, items are in very rough chronological order.
  - 1948-1951, Letters from Duke (Box 6)
  - 1952-1956, Letters (before Yale), (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1956, Letters at Yale (Box 6)
  - 1956 Sept.-1957 Jan. (Box 6)
  - 1956-1957, Letters re: Rochester (Box 6)
  - 1956-1957, Noyes Correspondence (Box 6)
  - 1957, Rochester relevant letters at Michigan (Box 6)
  - 1957, Letters at Michigan (Box 6)
  - 1957 Sept.-1958 Sept., (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1958 Sept.-1963 Sept., (10 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1962-1966, California negotiations (Box 7)
  - 1963 Sept.-1967 July, (9 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1967 July-1970 July, (9 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1970-1973, Journal of Economic Theory, some letters re: manuscripts (Box 9)
  - 1970 July-1971 July, (folder 1 of 3) (Box 9)
  - 1970 July-1971 July, (folders 2-3 of 3) (Box 10)
  - 1971 July-1973 July, (6 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1973, Guggenheim Application (Box 10)
  - 1973 July-1974 July, (folder 1 of 4) (Box 10)
  - 1973 July-1974 July, (folders 2-4 of 4) (Box 11)
  - 1974 July-1976 July, (6 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1976 July-1977 July, (folder 1 of 3) (Box 11)
  - 1976 July-1977 July, (folders 2-3 of 3) (Box 12)
  - 1977 July-1979 July, (6 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1977-1979, Letters re: Iosif Krass, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1978-1979, Correspondence at Cal Tech (Box 12)
  - 1979 July-1980 July, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1980-1981, Correspondence at Harvard, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1980 July-1981 July, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1981 May-Sept., Correspondence from Harvard (Box 13)
  - 1981 July-1984 June, (7 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1984 July-1985 June, (folders 1-2 of 3) (Box 14)
  - 1984 July-1985 June, (folder 3 of 3) (Box 15)
  - 1985 June-1988 June, (8 folders) (Box 15)
  - 1988 July-1989 June, Outgoing (Box 15)
  - 1988-1989, Incoming (Box 16)
  - 1989-1992, (6 folders) (Box 16)
  - 1992-1993, Incoming (Box 16)
  - 1993-1997, Outgoing, (7 folders) (Box 17)
  - 1997, Correspondence with Makoto Yano (Box 17)
  - 1997-2003 (Box 17)
  - 1998-2002, (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - 1998-2001, E-mail (Box 18)
  - Undated (Box 18)
- Course Materials Series, 1950s-1995 and undated, (5 boxes)
  Contains lecture notes, reading lists, class notes, exams, and other materials from throughout McKenzie's teaching career, with an emphasis on his courses at the University of Rochester. The bulk of the material is for his seminar on general equilibrium theory, including multiple versions of his handwritten text for the course. Series organized alphabetically by folder title.
  - Curriculum revision at Duke, 1950s (Box 18)
  - Economic theory, 1963-1968, 1978, 1981, (8 folders) (Box 18)
  - Economics 131 notes, 1958 (Box 18)
  - Exams, 1952-circa 1955 (Box 18)
  - Exams, Econ. 52, 1952-1954 (Box 18)
  - General equilibrium at Duke, 1953-1955, (3 folders) (Box 18)
  - General equilibrium exams, 1968-1995 (Box 19)
  - General equilibrium theory, 1969-1987, (22 folders) (Box 19)
  - General equilibrium theory, 1987-1992, 1995, (12 folders) (Box 20)
  - General equilibrium theory seminar notes, typed, 1995, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - General equilibrium theory notes, undated, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - General equilibrium theory notes, 1980s-1990s, and undated, (10 folders) (Box 21)
  - General equilibrium theory notes, 1978, circa 1981, (5 folders) (Box 22)
  - Harvard theory course and notes, circa 1981, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Harvard visit summer courses, 1980-1981 (Box 22)
  - Letters re: Michigan, 1956-1957 (Box 22)
  - Mathematical economics notes, 1950s, (3 folders) (Box 22)
  - Mathematical economics notes at Michigan, circa 1957 (Box 22)
  - Mathematical economics seminar, exams, old notes, etc, 1965-1983 (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 23)
  - Qualifying exams, 1960s-1980s (Box 23)
  - Values theory I, 1977 (Box 23)
  - Values theory II, 1960s-1980s, (3 folders) (Box 23)
- Organizations Series, 1956-1990s, (10 boxes)
  Consists of correspondence, papers, minutes, member lists, fellowship applications, and other written material related to national and international organizations with which McKenzie was involved. The bulk of the material relates to the Econometric Society, of which McKenzie was president in 1977, and the Mathematical Social Sciences Board, which he chaired from 1968 to 1970. Also included are records documenting McKenzie's involvement with American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Economic Association, the International Economic Review, the Journal of International Economics, the National Academy of Science, the National Research Council, the National Science Foundation, and the Social Sciences Council.
  The series is organized alphabetically by organization and by folder title, except for the Econometric Society folders which are chronological by year.
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1960s-1980s (Box 23)
  - American Economic Association, 1960s (Box 23)
  - Econometric Society, 1956-1993
    - 1956, Cleveland meeting (Box 23)
    - 1959-1973, Correspondence (Box 23)
    - 1960-1961, Materials including proposal to NSF (Box 24)
    - 1965, World Congress organizational correspondence (Box 24)
    - 1965, World Congress programs (Box 24)
    - 1969, Fellows, (3 folders) (Box 24)
    - 1970-1971, Econometrics volume (Box 24)
    - 1973, Fellow (Box 24)
    - 1974, Executive committee (Box 24)
    - 1974, Grenoble meeting (Box 24)
    - 1974-1976, Standing committee (Box 24)
    - 1975, Program (Box 24)
    - 1975, World Congress, (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - 1975-1976, Executive committee correspondence (Box 25)
    - 1975-1977, Econometrica (Box 25)
    - 1975-1978, Walras-Bowley lectures (Box 25)
    - 1976, Madison meeting (Box 25)
    - 1976, Ottawa meeting (Box 25)
    - 1976, Executive committee meeting, Ottawa (Box 25)
    - 1976, Helsinki meeting (Box 25)
    - 1976-1977, Summer meetings, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - 1976-1977, Presidency (Box 25)
    - 1977, New York meeting: fellows and standing committee, (3 folders) (Box 25)
    - 1977, Nominating committee for fellowships, (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - 1977, Nominating committee for officers and council (Box 26)
    - 1977, Marschak fund (Box 26)
    - 1977, Helsinki affair (Box 26)
    - 1977, World Congress (Box 26)
    - 1977, Presidential matters, (3 folders) (Box 26)
    - 1977, South American meeting (Box 26)
    - 1977, Miscellaneous (Box 26)
    - 1977-1978, Aide memoire (Box 26)
    - 1978, Chicago meeting (Box 27)
    - 1978, Geneva meeting (Box 27)
    - 1978, June, Boulder meeting (Box 27)
    - 1978, Vienna meeting (Box 27)
    - 1978, Past presidents (Box 27)
    - 1978 July-1979 July, Correspondence, (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - 1981 July-1986 Dec., Correspondence and other materials (Box 27)
    - 1988-1989, Treasurer committee correspondence (Box 27)
    - 1993, Selection of officers (Box 27)
  - International Economic Review, 1970s (Box 27)
  - Journal of International Economics, 1970-1972 (Box 28)
  - Mathematical Social Sciences Board, 1957-1975
    - Chairman, 1967-1970, (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - Committee on history, 1960s, (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - Dynamic systems seminar, 1975 (Box 28)
    - Economy committee, 1966-1974, (folder 1 of 3) (Box 28)
    - Economy committee, 1966-1974, (folders 2-3 of 3) (Box 29)
    - Final report of summer institute, 1957 (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous material, 1960s, (4 folders) (Box 29)
    - New proposals, 1968, (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - Postscript, 1970-1973 (Box 29)
    - Proposal, 1970, (2 folders) (Box 30)
    - Raiffa's conference, 1966 (Box 30)
    - Summer conference, 1965-1966 (Box 30)
    - Summer workshop, Berkeley, 1971 (Box 30)
  - National Academy of Science, 1980-1984, (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - National Academy of Science, 1970s-1990s, (9 folders) (Box 31)
  - National Research Council, 1960s-1970s, (4 folders) (Box 31)
  - National Research Council, 1960-1962 (Box 32)
  - National Science Foundation, 1960-1970, (4 folders) (Box 32)
  - Social Sciences Council, 1960-1962 (Box 32)
- Personal Files Series, 1942-2004 and undated, (1 box)
  Contains curriculum vitae, personal correspondence mostly from the 1990s, graduate school materials, newspaper articles and clippings, and other items of personal and biographical interest. Catalog of McKenzie library held by the Institute of Economic Research in Japan is in English and Japanese. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Catalog of Lionel W. McKenzie Library [Institute of Economic Research, Kyoto University], 2004 (Box 32)
  - Curriculum vitae, circa 1950-2003 (Box 32)
  - Graduate school materials, 1942-1949 (Box 32)
  - Japan trip, 1980 (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 32)
  - Newspaper articles, press releases, and years in review, 1950s-1999 (Box 32)
  - Personal correspondence, 1952-1998 (Box 32)
- Research and Writings Series, 1946-1999 and undated, (12 boxes)
  Notes, manuscripts, drafts, proofs, and reprints for many of McKenzie's publications spanning his entire career. Includes his Princeton thesis and manuscripts of a few unpublished articles. Major topics include the turnpike theorem, general equilibrium, and optimal economic growth, with extensive notes and drafts for writings on all three topics. A few folders house correspondence pertaining to specific articles and areas of research, often including comments and critiques of McKenzie's ideas by his peers. Also included are McKenzie's contributions to the 1987 New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics, the 1983 Handbook of Mathematical Economics, and the International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences. Additionally, there is a small group of bound material from graduate courses McKenzie took in the 1950s with McKenzie's annotations. Folders arranged alphabetically by title. For published articles, the date refers to the date of publication.
  - Accumulation Programs of Maximum Utility and the Von Neumann Facet, 1967 (Box 33)
  - Bibliographies, circa 1953, circa 1960, (2 folders) (Box 33)
  - Book, early plans, circa 1955 (Box 33)
  - Capital Accumulation Optimal in the Final State, 1971 (Box 33)
  - The Classical Theorem on Existence of Competitive Equilibrium, 1981, (5 folders) (Box 33)
  - The Classical Theorem on Existence of Competitive Equilibrium: a Postscript (unpublished), circa 1981 (Box 33)
  - Competitive Equilibrium with Dependent Consumer Preferences, 1956 (Box 33)
  - The Comparative Statics and Dynamics of Stationary States, 1990, (folders 1-4 of 5) (Box 33)
  - The Comparative Statics and Dynamics of Stationary States, 1990, (folder 5 of 5) (Box 34)
  - A Contribution to the Theorem of Competitive Equilibrium, early versions, circa 1960s (Box 34)
  - Copies of articles, 1946-1999, (6 folders) (Box 34)
  - Core and Competitive Equilibria in Finite Economies, 1993 (Box 34)
  - Cowles Foundation discussion papers, 1956 (Box 34)
  - Demand Theory Without a Utility Index, 1957 (Box 34)
  - Department papers, 1961 (Box 34)
  - Department seminars, 1984 (Box 34)
  - Distribution lists, 1970s-1980s and undated (Box 35)
  - "The Dorfman-Samuelson-Solow Turnpike Theorem," 1963, (2 folders) (Box 35)
  - "Early Conferences on Economic Growth," 1999 (Box 35)
  - Early versions of 1960s papers (Box 35)
  - "Equality of Factor Prices in World Trade," 1955 (Box 35)
  - "On Equilibrium in Graham's Model of World Trade and Other Competitive Systems," 1954, (2 folders) (Box 35)
  - "Equilibrium, Trade, and Capital Accumulation," 1999, (2 folders) (Box 35)
  - "The Existence of Competitive Equilibrium in a Growing Economy," 1993 (Box 35)
  - "The Existence of Competitive Equilibrium Over an Infinite Horizon with Production and General Consumption Sets," 1993 (Box 35)
  - "On the Existence of General Equilibrium," 1959, (folder 1 of 3) (Box 35)
  - "On the Existence of General Equilibrium," 1959, (folders 2-3 of 3) (Box 36)
  - "Factor Price Equilization and the Jacobian Determinant," 1963, (3 folders) (Box 36)
  - "A General Equilibrium Analysis in International Trade," circa 1963 (Box 36)
  - "Ideal Output and the Independence of Firms," 1951 (Box 36)
  - Indirect tax problem, circa 1956 (Box 36)
  - Japanese students at the University of Rochester, 1970s-1980s (Box 36)
  - Kimura (JET), 1973-1974 (Box 36)
  - Lectures, undated (Box 36)
  - Letter of application for research support, circa 1953 (Box 36)
  - Materials for Stanford workshop, 1956 (Box 36)
  - "Mathematical Theory of International Trade," 1965 (Box 36)
  - "Maximal Paths in the Von Neumann Model," 1967, (3 folders) (Box 36)
  - Miscellaneous materials and manuscripts, undated, (5 folders) (Box 37)
  - MIT press reprints, 1970s (Box 37)
  - My papers at the University of Rochester, 1960s, (2 folders) (Box 37)
  - New Palgrave Dictionary, 1980s
    - General, 1980s, (2 folders) (Box 37)
    - "General Equilibrium," 1987, (3 folders) (Box 38)
    - "Gross Substitutes," 1987 (Box 38)
    - "Turnpike Theory," 1987, (2 folders) (Box 38)
  - "A New Route to Turnpikes," 1976 (Box 38)